<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>HornetQ REST Interface</title>

    <releaseinfo>1.0-beta-1</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <preface id="preface" revision="1">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>Commercial development support, production support and training for
    RESTEasy and HornetQ is available through JBoss, a division of Red Hat
    Inc. (see http://www.jboss.com/).</para>

    <para></para>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The HornetQ REST interface allows you to leverage the reliability
    and scalability features of HornetQ over a simple REST/HTTP interface.
    Messages are produced and consumed by sending and receiving simple HTTP
    messages that contain the content you want to push around. For instance,
    here's a simple example of posting an order to an order processing queue
    express as an HTTP message:</para>

    <para><programlisting>POST /queue/orders/create HTTP/1.1
Host: example.com
Content-Type: application/xml

&lt;order&gt;
   &lt;name&gt;Bill&lt;/name&gt;
   &lt;item&gt;iPhone 4&lt;/item&gt;
   &lt;cost&gt;$199.99&lt;/cost&gt;
&lt;/order
</programlisting>As you can see, we're just posting some arbitrary XML
    document to a URL. When the XML is received on the server is it processed
    within HornetQ as a JMS message and distributed through core HornetQ.
    Simple and easy. Consuming messages from a queue or topic looks very
    similar. We'll discuss the entire interface in detail later in this
    docbook.</para>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Goals of REST Interface</title>

      <para>Why would you want to use HornetQ's REST interface? What are the
      goals of the REST interface?</para>

      <para></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Zero client footprint. We want HornetQ to be usable by any
          client/programming language that has an adequate HTTP client
          library. You shouldn't have to download, install, and configure a
          special library to interact with HornetQ.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lightweight interoperability. The HTTP protocol is strong
          enough to be our message exchange protocol. Since interactions are
          RESTful the HTTP uniform interface provides all the interoperability
          you need to communicate between different languages, platforms, and
          even messaging implementations that choose to implement the same
          RESTful interface as HornetQ (i.e. the <ulink
          url="http://rest-star.org">REST-*</ulink> effort.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No envelope (i.e. SOAP) or feed (i.e. Atom) format
          requirements. You shouldn't have to learn and use a specific XML
          document format in order to send and receive messages through
          HornetQ's REST interface.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Leverage the reliability, scalability, and clustering features
          of HornetQ on the back end without sacrificing the simplicity of a
          REST interface.</para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation and Configuration</title>

    <para></para>
  </chapter>
</book>
