<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="oauth2">
    <title>OAuth 2.0 and Resteasy Skeleton Key</title>
    <para>
        The overall goal of Resteasy Skeleton Key is to provide a unified way for both Browser and JAX-RS clients
        to be secured in an integrated and seemless fashion.  We want to support a network of applications and
        services so that if one server needs to execute or forward requests to another, there is a secure and
        scalable way to do this without hitting a central authentication server each and every request.
    </para>
    <para>
        The <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6749">OAuth 2.0</ulink> Authorization Framework enables a
        third-party to obtain access to an HTTP resource on behalf of a resource owner without the third-party
        having to know the credentials of the resource owner.  It does this by issuing access tokens via a browser
        redirect protocol, or by a direct grant.  The access tokens can then be transmitted by the <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-v2-bearer-23">OAuth2 Bearer Token</ulink>
        protocol to access the protected resource.
    </para>
    <para>
        Resteasy Skeleton Key is an OAuth 2.0 implementation that allows you to use existing JBoss AS7 security infrastructure
        to secure your web applications and restful services.  You can turn an existing web app into an OAuth 2.0 Access
        Token Provider or you can turn a JBoss AS7 Security Domain into a central authentication and authorization
        server that a whole host of applications and services can use.  Here are the features in a nutshell:
    </para>
    <para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Turn an existing servlet-form-auth-based web application into an OAuth 2.0 provider.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Provide Distributed Single-Sign-On (SSO) from a central authentication server.  Log in once, and
                you can securely access any browser-based app configured to work in the domain.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Provide Distributed Logout.  Following one link from any application can log you out of all your
                distributed applications configured to use SSO.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Web apps can interact securely with any remote restful service by forwarding access tokens through
                the standard Authorization header.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Access tokens are digitally signed by the oauth2 framework and can be used to access any service
                configured to work in the domain.  The tokens contain both identity and role mapping information.  Because
                they are digitally signed, there's no need to overload the central authentication server with each request
                to verify identity and to determine permissions.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <important>
        <para>The Resteasy distribution comes with an OAuth2 Skeleton key example.  This is a great way to see
            OAuth2 in action and how it is configured.  You may also want to use this as a template for your applications.
        </para>
    </important>

    <section>
        <title>System Requirements</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>JBoss AS 7.1.x or higher</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HTTPS is required.  See the JBoss 7 documentation on how to enable SSL for web applications</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Resteasy 3.0 or higher must be installed within your AS7 distribution.  View how to <link linkend="upgrading-as7">upgrade AS7</link>
                to the latest version of Resteasy.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A username/password based JBoss security domain</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Browser-based apps must be configured to use servlet FORM authentication and web.xml security
                constraints</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
     </section>
    <section>
        <title>Generate the Security Domain Key Pair</title>
        <para>
            Access tokens are digitally signed and verified by an RSA keypair.  You must generate this keypair using
            the JDK's keytool command or by something like openssl.
        </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ keytool -genkey -alias mydomain -keyalg rsa -keystore realm.jks
]]></programlisting>
        <para>
            This will ask you a series of questions that will be used to create the X509 public certificate. Basic PKI
            stuff that you hopefully are already familiar with.  Move this keystore file into a directory that you can
            reference from a configuration file.  I suggest the standalone/configuration directory of your JBoss AS7
            distribution.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Setting up the Auth Server</title>
        <para>The next thing you're gonna want to do is set up a web application to be your OAuth2 provider.
        This can be an existing web app or you can create a new WAR to be your central authentication server.
        An existing web app must be configured to use servlet FORM authentication.  Enabling OAuth2 within
        this app will not change how normal users interact with it.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Setting up your Security Domain</title>
            <para>
                You can use any set of JBoss AS7 login modules you want to store your username, passwords and role mappings.
                Each security domain will be comprised of regular users, oauth clients, and admins.  Oauth clients
                represent either a web application that wants to use the auth-server to do SSO, or they are traditional
                oauth clients that want access permision to act on behalf of another user (the traditional OAuth use case).
                Every oauth client must have a username, password, and a specific role mapping that gives them various permissions to
                participate in OAuth 2 protocols.  There is a role that grants an oauth client permission
                to login as a specific user (default is <literal>login</literal>.  This is the SSO case.  There is a role that grants a client permission
                to request permission to act on behalf of a user (default is <literal>oauth</literal>).  Additional
                role mappings assigned to the oauth client define what additional permissions they are allowed to have.  These
                additional permissions are the role mappings of the application and are the intersection of the permissions
                given to the user the client is acting on behalf of.  This is better explained by an example role mapping file:
           </para>
<programlisting>
wburke=user,admin
loginclient=login
oauthclient1=oauth,*
oauthclient2=oauth,user
</programlisting>
            <para>
                In the above role mapping file with have a simple user <literal>wburke</literal>.  He has application
                role permissions of <literal>user</literal> and <literal>admin</literal>.  One oauth client user
                is <literal>loginclient</literal>.  It has been given a role mapping of <literal>login</literal>.
                This client is allowed to login as the user and is given all roles of the user.  The <literal>oauthclient1</literal>
                user is not allowed to login as the user, but is allowed to obtain an OAuth grant to act on behalf of the
                user.  The <literal>*</literal> role means that <literal>oauthclient1</literal> is granted the same
                roles as the user it is acting on behalf of.  If <literal>oauthclient1</literal> acts on behalf of
                <literal>wburke</literal> then it will have both <literal>user</literal> and <literal>admin</literal> permissions.
                The <literal>oauthclient2</literal> is also allowed to use the oauth grant protocol, but it will only
                ever be granted <literal>user</literal> permissions.
            </para>
            <para>
                You are not confined to login, oauth, and * as role mapping names.  You can configure them to
                be whatever you want.
            </para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Why have different login and oauth role mappings?</emphasis>  <literal>login</literal> clients
                are allowed to bypass entering username and password if the user has already logged in once and has
                an existing authenticated session with the server.  <literal>oauth</literal> clients are <emphasis>always</emphasis>
                required to enter username and password.  You probably don't want to grant permission automatically to
                an oauth client.  A user will want to look at who is requesting permission.  This role distinction
                gives you this capability.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Auth Server Config File</title>
            <para>You must create a configuration file that holds all the configuration for OAuth2.  This is json formatted
            If you name it <literal>resteasy-oauth.json</literal> and put it within the <literal>WEB-INF/</literal>
            directory of your war, that's all you have to do.  Otherwise, you must specify the full path
            to this configuration file within a context-param within your web.xml file.  The name of this param
            is <literal>skeleton.key.config.file</literal>.  You can reference System properties within the
            value of this context-param by enclosing them within <literal>${VARIABLE}</literal>.  Here's an
            example configuration:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
{
   "realm" : "mydomain",
   "admin-role" : "admin",
   "login-role" : "login",
   "oauth-client-role" : "oauth",
   "wildcard-role" : "*",
   "realm-keystore" : "${jboss.server.config.dir}/realm.jks",
   "realm-key-alias" : "mydomain",
   "realm-keystore-password" : "password",
   "realm-private-key-password" : "password",
   "truststore" : "${jboss.server.config.dir}/client-truststore.ts",
   "truststore-password" : "password",
   "resources" : [
      "https://example.com/customer-portal",
      "https://somewhere.com/product-portal"
   ]
}
]]></programlisting>
            <para>
                Let's go over what each of these config variables represent:
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>realm</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Name of the realm representing the users of your distributed applications and services
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>admin-role</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Admin role mapping used for admins.  You must have this defined if you want to
                                do distributed logout.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>login-role</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Role mapping for login clients.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>oauth-client-role</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Role mapping for regular oauth clients.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>wildcard-role</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Role mapping for assigning all roles to an oauth client wishing to act on behalf of a user.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>realm-keystore</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Absolute path pointing to the keystore that contains the realm's keypair.  This keypair
                                is used to digitally sign access tokens.  You may use <literal>${VARIABLE}</literal>
                                to reference System properties.  The example is referencing the JBoss config dir.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>realm-key-alias</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Key alias for the key pair stored in your realm-keystore file.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>realm-keystore-password</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Password to access the keystore.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>realm-private-key-password</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Password to access the private realm key within the keystore
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>truststore</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Used for outgoing client HTTPS communications.  This contains one or more trusted
                                host certificates or certificate authorities.  This is OPTIONAL if you are not
                                using distributed logout.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>truststore-password</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Password for the truststore keystore.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>resources</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Root URLs of applications using this auth-server for SSO.  This is OPTIONAL and only
                                needed if you want to allow distributed logout.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up web.xml</title>
            <para>
                Set up your security constraints however you like.  You must though use FORM authentication.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up jboss-web.xml</title>
            <para>
                In jboss-web.xml in your WEB-INF directory, point to your security domain as a normal secured web app does,
                and also use a specific valve.
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<jboss-web>
    <security-domain>java:/jaas/commerce</security-domain>
    <valve>
        <class-name>org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton.key.as7.OAuthAuthenticationServerValve</class-name>
    </valve>
</jboss-web>]]></programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up jboss-deployment-structure.xml</title>
            <para>
                You must import the skeleton key modules so that the classes are visible to this application.  Include
                this file within WEB-INF
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<jboss-deployment-structure>
    <deployment>
        <dependencies>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.resteasy-jaxrs" services="import"/>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.resteasy-jackson-provider" services="import"/>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton-key"/>
        </dependencies>
    </deployment>
</jboss-deployment-structure>]]></programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Tweak your login page</title>
            <para>
                The action url used by your login form is dependent on the oauth protocol.  Skeleton key defines
                a request attribute called <literal>OAUTH_FORM_ACTION</literal> which is the URL you should
                use for the form's action.  Here's an example login.jsp page that uses this attribute:
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<form action="<%= request.getAttribute("OAUTH_FORM_ACTION")%>" method=post>
    <p><strong>Please Enter Your User Name: </strong>
    <input type="text" name="j_username" size="25">
    <p><p><strong>Please Enter Your Password: </strong>
    <input type="password" size="15" name="j_password">
    <p><p>
    <input type="submit" value="Submit">
    <input type="reset" value="Reset">
</form>
]]></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Setting Up An App for SSO</title>
        <para>
            This section specifies how you can use the central auth-server for SSO.  Following these directions will
            use the auth-server for browser log in.  The server will also be able to do bearer token authentication as well.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>SSO config file</title>
            <para>
                The best way to create the config file for your application is to ask the central authentication server
                you configured in the last section.  So, boot up the auth server and go to https://<emphasis>auth-server-context-root</emphasis>/j_oauth_realm_info.html.
                For example: <literal>https://localhost:8443/auth-server/j_oauth_realm_info.html</literal>. This will
                show template configurations depending on which valve you are using.  You want the <literal>OAuthManagedResourceValve</literal> config.
                It will look something like this.
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
{
  "realm" : "mydomain",
  "realm-public-key" : "MIGfMA0GCSqGSIb3DQEBAQUAA4GNADCBiQKBgQCO8XXyi7oAq5ecsYy+tJrl54N2TtKAkxuWEDmzvSPU+mUA2/3qHcxucZakG74Z49410tn5IIu2CXXlk9CuKcpXvKh+cPBzmC1Nmbd+4MelRVVZnvogyPICs8h3sNTAMNdfI6hDc5/MfVQQ9m5OZrKbNR3dY50mTi/ExnJ5IWPqxQIDAQAB",
  "admin-role" : "admin",
  "auth-url" : "https://localhost:8443/auth-server/login.jsp",
  "code-url" : "https://localhost:8443/auth-server/j_oauth_resolve_access_code",
  "truststore" : "REQUIRED",
  "truststore-password" : "REQUIRED",
  "client-id" : "REQUIRED",
  "client-credentials" : {
    "password" : "REQUIRED"
  }
}]]></programlisting>
            Let's go over what each of these config variables represent:
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>realm</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Name of the realm representing the users of your distributed applications and services
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>realm-public-key</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            PEM format of public key.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>admin-role</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Admin role mapping used for admins.  You must have this defined if you want to
                            do distributed logout.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>auth-url</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            URL of the auth server's login page.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>code-url</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            URL to turn an access code into an access token. (Part of the OAuth2 protocol)
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>truststore</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Used for outgoing client HTTPS communications.  This contains one or more trusted
                            host certificates or certificate authorities.  This is REQUIRED as you must talk
                            HTTPS to the auth server to turn an access code into an access token.  You can
                            create this truststore by extracting the public certificate of the auth server's SSL
                            keystore.  The google knows if you want to know how to do this.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>truststore-password</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Password for the truststore keystore.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>client-id</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Username of the login client.  This server will send client-id and password when
                            turning an access code into an access token.  Internally, the server will do an HTTPS
                            invocation to the auth-server passing this information using Basic AUTH.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>client-credentials</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Must specify the password of the oauth login client.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up web.xml</title>
            <para>
                Set up your security constraints however you like.  You must though use FORM authentication.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up jboss-web.xml</title>
            <para>
                In jboss-web.xml in your WEB-INF directory you need to use a specific valve.
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<jboss-web>
    <valve>
        <class-name>org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton.key.as7.OAuthManagedResourceValve</class-name>
    </valve>
</jboss-web>]]></programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up jboss-deployment-structure.xml</title>
            <para>
                You must import the skeleton key modules so that the classes are visible to this application.  Include
                this file within WEB-INF
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<jboss-deployment-structure>
    <deployment>
        <dependencies>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.resteasy-jaxrs" services="import"/>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.resteasy-jackson-provider" services="import"/>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton-key"/>
        </dependencies>
    </deployment>
</jboss-deployment-structure>]]></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Bearer Token only Setup</title>
        <para>
            If you have a web app that you want only to allow Bearer token authentication, i.e. a set of JAX-RS services
            then follow these directions.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Bearer token auth config file</title>
            <para>
                The best way to create the config file for your application is to ask the central authentication server
                you configured in the last section.  So, boot up the auth server and go to https://<emphasis>auth-server-context-root</emphasis>/j_oauth_realm_info.html.
                For example: <literal>https://localhost:8443/auth-server/j_oauth_realm_info.html</literal>. This will
                show template configurations depending on which valve you are using.  You want the <literal>BearerTokenAuthenticatorValve</literal> config.
                It will look something like this.
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
{
  "realm" : "mydomain",
  "realm-public-key" : "MIGfMA0GCSqGSIb3DQEBAQUAA4GNADCBiQKBgQCO8XXyi7oAq5ecsYy+tJrl54N2TtKAkxuWEDmzvSPU+mUA2/3qHcxucZakG74Z49410tn5IIu2CXXlk9CuKcpXvKh+cPBzmC1Nmbd+4MelRVVZnvogyPICs8h3sNTAMNdfI6hDc5/MfVQQ9m5OZrKbNR3dY50mTi/ExnJ5IWPqxQIDAQAB",
}]]></programlisting>
            All that is needed is the realm name, and the public key of the realm.
            Let's go over what each of these config variables represent:
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>realm</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Name of the realm representing the users of your distributed applications and services
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>realm-public-key</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            PEM format of the realm's public key.  Used to verify tokens.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up web.xml</title>
            <para>
                Set up your security constraints however you like.  You must though use FORM authentication.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up jboss-web.xml</title>
            <para>
                In jboss-web.xml in your WEB-INF directory you need to use a specific valve.
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<jboss-web>
    <valve>
        <class-name>org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton.key.as7.BearerTokenAuthenticatorValve</class-name>
    </valve>
</jboss-web>]]></programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Set up jboss-deployment-structure.xml</title>
            <para>
                You must import the skeleton key modules so that the classes are visible to this application.  Include
                this file within WEB-INF
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<jboss-deployment-structure>
    <deployment>
        <dependencies>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.resteasy-jaxrs" services="import"/>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.resteasy-jackson-provider" services="import"/>
            <module name="org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton-key"/>
        </dependencies>
    </deployment>
</jboss-deployment-structure>]]></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Obtaining an access token programmatically.</title>
        <para>
            You can request an access token from the auth-server by doing a simple HTTPS invocation.  You must
            use BASIC authentication to identify your user, and you will get back a signed access token for that user.
            Here's an example using a JAX-RS 2.0 client:
        </para>
<programlisting>
    ResteasyClient client = new ResteasyClientBuilder()
                                .truststore(truststore)
                                .build();

    Form form = new Form().param("grant_type", "client_credentials");
    ResteasyWebTarget target = client.target("https://localhost:8443/auth-server/j_oauth_token_grant");
    target.configuration().register(new BasicAuthentication("bburke@redhat.com", "password"));
    AccessTokenResponse res = target.request()
                           .post(Entity.form(form), AccessTokenResponse.class);
</programlisting>
        <para>
           The above makes a simple POST to the context root of the auth server with <literal>j_oauth_token_grant</literal>
            at the end of the target URL.  This resource is responsible for creating access tokens.
        </para>
 <programlisting><![CDATA[
    try
    {
       Response response = client.target("https://localhost:8443/database/products").request()
                               .header(HttpHeaders.AUTHORIZATION, "Bearer " + res.getToken()).get();
       String xml = response.readEntity(String.class);
    }
    finally
    {
       client.close();
    }
]]></programlisting>
        <para>
            The access token is a simple string.  To invoke on a service protected by bearer token auth, just
            set the <literal>Authorization</literal> header of your HTTPS request with a value of <literal>Bearer</literal>
            and then the access token string.
        </para>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Access remote services securely in a secure web session</title>
        <para>
            If you have an application secured by one of the methods described in this chapter, you can obtain
            the access token of the current web session so that you can use it to invoke on other remote services
            securely using bearer token authentication.  Each HttpServletRequest in a secure web session has an attribute
            called <literal>org.jboss.resteasy.skeleton.key.SkeletonKeySession</literal> which points to an instance
            of a class with the same  name.  This class contains the access token and also points to the truststore
            you configured.  You can then extract this info and make secure remote invocations.  Here's an example of that.
        </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
   public List<String> getCustomers(HttpServletRequest request)
   {
      SkeletonKeySession session = (SkeletonKeySession)request.getAttribute(SkeletonKeySession.class.getName());
      ResteasyClient client = new ResteasyClientBuilder()
                 .truststore(session.getMetadata().getTruststore())
                 .build();
      try
      {
         Response response = client.target("https://localhost:8443/database/customers").request()
                 .header(HttpHeaders.AUTHORIZATION, "Bearer " + session.getToken()).get();
         return response.readEntity(new GenericType<List<String>>(){});
      }
      finally
      {
         client.close();
      }
   }
        ]]>
</programlisting>
        <para>
            If you are within a JAX-RS environment you can inject a <literal>SkeletonKeySession</literal> using the <literal>@Context</literal> annotation.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Check Out the OAuth2 Example!</title>
        <important>
          <para>The Resteasy distribution comes with an example project that shows all of these different features in action!  Check it out!</para>
        </important>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Auth Server Action URLs</title>
        <para>
            For reference, here is the set of relative URL actions that the auth server will publish.
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis>login page</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The is the url of your login page.  OAuth clients will redirect to it.  This is application
                            specific.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>j_oauth_resolve_access_code</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Used by oauth clients to turn an access code into an access token.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>j_oauth_logout</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Do a GET request to this URL and it will perform a distributed logout.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>j_oauth_token_grant</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Do a POST with BASIC Auth to obtain an access token for a specific user.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>j_oauth_realm_info.html</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Displays an HTML page with template configurations for using this realm.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>