<chapter id="RESTEasy_Client_Framework">
    <title>Client Framework</title>

    <para>

        The Resteasy Client Framework is the mirror opposite of the JAX-RS server-side specification. Instead of using
        JAX-RS annotations to map an incoming request to your RESTFul Web Service method, the client framework builds an
        HTTP request that it uses to invoke on a remote RESTful Web Service. This remote service does not have to be a
        JAX-RS service and can be any web resource that accepts HTTP requests.
    </para>
    <para>

        Resteasy has a client proxy framework that allows you to use JAX-RS annotations to invoke on a remote HTTP
        resource.
        The way it works is that you write a Java interface and use JAX-RS annotations on methods and the interface. For
        example:
    </para>
    <para>

<programlisting>
public interface SimpleClient
{
   @GET
   @Path("basic")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   String getBasic();

   @PUT
   @Path("basic")
   @Consumes("text/plain")
   void putBasic(String body);

   @GET
   @Path("queryParam")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   String getQueryParam(@QueryParam("param")String param);

   @GET
   @Path("matrixParam")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   String getMatrixParam(@MatrixParam("param")String param);

   @GET
   @Path("uriParam/{param}")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   int getUriParam(@PathParam("param")int param);
}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>

        Resteasy has a simple API based on Apache HttpClient. You generate a proxy then you can invoke methods on the
        proxy. The invoked method gets translated to an HTTP request based on how you annotated the method and posted to
        the server. Here's how you would set this up:
    </para>
    <para>

        <programlisting>
            import org.jboss.resteasy.client.ProxyFactory;
            ...
            // this initialization only needs to be done once per VM
            RegisterBuiltin.register(ResteasyProviderFactory.getInstance());


            SimpleClient client = ProxyFactory.create(SimpleClient.class, "http://localhost:8081");
            client.putBasic("hello world");
        </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>

        Please see the ProxyFactory javadoc for more options. For instance, you may want to fine tune the HttpClient
        configuration.
    </para>
    <para>


    </para>
    <para>

        @CookieParam works the mirror opposite of its server-side counterpart and creates a cookie header to send to the
        server. You do not need to use @CookieParam if you allocate your own javax.ws.rs.core.Cookie object and pass it
        as
        a parameter to a client proxy method. The client framework understands that you are passing a cookie to the
        server
        so no extra metadata is needed.
    </para>
    <para>


    </para>
    <para>

        The client framework can use the same providers available on the server. You must manually register them through
        the ResteasyProviderFactory singleton using the addMessageBodyReader() and addMessageBodyWriter() methods.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
        ResteasyProviderFactory.getInstance().addMessageBodyReader(MyReader.class);
    </programlisting>
    <para>
     The framework also supports the JAX-RS locator pattern, but on the client side.  So, if you have a method annotated only with @Path, that proxy method
     will return a new proxy of the interface returned by that method.
    </para>
    <sect1 id="Custom_client-side_responses">
        <title>Abstract Responses</title>

        <para>

            Sometimes you are interested not only in the response body of a client request, but also either the response
            code and/or response headers. The Client-Proxy framework has two ways to get at this information
        </para>
        <para>


        </para>
        <para>

            You may return a javax.ws.rs.core.Response.Status enumeration from your method calls:
        </para>
        <para>

            <programlisting>
@Path("/")
public interface MyProxy {
   @POST
   Response.Status updateSite(MyPojo pojo);
}
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>

            Internally, after invoking on the server, the client proxy internals will convert the HTTP response code into
            a
            Response.Status enum.
        </para>
        <para>


        </para>
        <para>

            If you are interested in everything, you can get it with the org.jboss.resteasy.spi.ClientResponse interface:
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
/**
 * Response extension for the RESTEasy client framework. Use this, or Response
 * in your client proxy interface method return type declarations if you want
 * access to the response entity as well as status and header information.
 *
 * @author <a href="mailto:bill@burkecentral.com">Bill Burke</a>
 * @version $Revision: 1 $
 */
public abstract class ClientResponse<T> extends Response
{
   /**
    * This method returns the same exact map as Response.getMetadata() except as a map of strings 
    * rather than objects.
    *
    * @return
    */
   public abstract MultivaluedMap<String, String> getHeaders();

   public abstract Response.Status getResponseStatus();

   /**
    * Unmarshal the target entity from the response OutputStream.  You must have type information
    * set via <T> otherwise, this will not work.
    * <p/>
    * This method actually does the reading on the OutputStream.  It will only do the read once.  
    * Afterwards, it will cache the result and return the cached result.
    *
    * @return
    */
   public abstract T getEntity();

   /**
    * Extract the response body with the provided type information
    * <p/>
    * This method actually does the reading on the OutputStream.  It will only do the read once.  
    * Afterwards, it will cache the result and return the cached result.
    *
    * @param type
    * @param genericType
    * @param <T2>
    * @return
    */
   public abstract <T2> T2 getEntity(Class<T2> type, Type genericType);

   /**
    * Extract the response body with the provided type information.  GenericType is a trick used to
    * pass in generic type information to the resteasy runtime.
    * <p/>
    * For example:
    * <pre>
    * List<String> list = response.getEntity(new GenericType<List<String>() {});
    * <p/>
    * <p/>
    * This method actually does the reading on the OutputStream.  It will only do the read once.  Afterwards, it will
    * cache the result and return the cached result.
    *
    * @param type
    * @param <T2>
    * @return
    */
   public abstract <T2> T2 getEntity(GenericType<T2> type);
}
]]>
        </programlisting>
        <para>
            All the getEntity() methods are deferred until you invoke them. In other words, the response OutputStream is
            not read
            until you call one of these methods. The empty parameter getEntity() method can only be used if you have
            templated the ClientResponse within your method declaration. Resteasy uses this generic type information to
            know what type to unmarshal the raw OutputStream into. The other two getEntity() methods that take
            parameters, allow you to specify which Object types you want to marshal the response into. These methods
            allow you to dynamically extract whatever types you want at runtime. Here's an example:
        </para>
        <para>

            <programlisting>
@Path("/")
public interface LibraryService {

   @GET
   @Produces("application/xml")
   ClientResponse&lt;LibraryPojo&gt; getAllBooks();
}</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>

            We need to include the LibraryPojo in ClientResponse's generic declaration so that the client proxy
            framework
            knows how to unmarshal the HTTP response body.
        </para>
        <para>


        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sharing_interfaces">
        <title>Sharing an interface between client and server</title>
        <para>
            It is generally possible to share an interface between the client and server. In this scenario, you just
            have your JAX-RS services implement an annotated interface
            and then reuse that same interface to create client proxies to invoke on the client-side. One caveat to
            this is when your JAX-RS methods return a Response object.
            The problem on the client is that the client does not have any type information with a raw Response return
            type declaration. There are two ways of getting around
            this. The first is to use the @ClientResponseType annotation.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
import org.jboss.resteasy.annotations.ClientResponseType;
import javax.ws.rs.core.Response;

@Path("/")
public interface MyInterface {

   @GET
   @ClientResponseType(String.class)
   @Produces("text/plain")
   public Response get();
}</programlisting>
        <para>
            This approach isn't always good enough. The problem is that some MessageBodyReaders and Writers need generic
            type information in order to match and service a request.
        </para>
<programlisting>
@Path("/")
public interface MyInterface {

   @GET
   @Produces("application/xml")
   public Response getMyListOfJAXBObjects();
}</programlisting>
        <para>
            In this case, your client code can cast the returned Response object to a ClientResponse and use one of the
            typed getEntity() methods.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
MyInterface proxy = ProxyFactory.create(MyInterface.class, "http://localhost:8081");
ClientResponse response = (ClientResponse)proxy.getMyListOfJAXBObjects();
List<MyJaxbClass> list = response.getEntity(new GenericType<List<MyJaxbClass>>());
]]></programlisting>

    </sect1>
    
    
    
    <sect1 id="Client_error_handling">
        <title>Client Error Handling</title>

        <para>

            If you are using the Client Framework and your proxy methods return something other than a
            ClientResponse, then the default client error handling comes into play. Any response code that is greater
            than 399 will automatically cause a org.jboss.resteasy.client.ClientResponseFailure exception
        </para>
        <para>

<programlisting>
   @GET
   ClientResponse&lt;String&gt; get() // will throw an exception if you call getEntity()

   @GET
   MyObject get(); // will throw a ClientResponseFailure on response code &gt; 399
</programlisting>
        </para>


	<para>
		In cases where Client Proxy methods do not return Response or
		ClientResponse, it may be not be desirable for the Client Proxy
		Framework to throw generic ClientResponseFailure exceptions. In these
		scenarios, where more fine-grained control of thrown Exceptions is
		required, the ClientErrorInterceptor API may be used.
		</para>
<programlisting>
public static T getClientService(final Class clazz, final String serverUri)
{
	ResteasyProviderFactory pf = ResteasyProviderFactory.getInstance();
	pf.addClientErrorInterceptor(new DataExceptionInterceptor());

	System.out.println("Generating REST service for: " + clazz.getName());
	return ProxyFactory.create(clazz, serverUri);
}
</programlisting>

<para>
	ClientErrorInterceptor provides a hook into the proxy ClientResponse request lifecycle. If a
	Client Proxy method is called, resulting in a client exception, and the
	proxy return type is not Response or ClientResponse, registered
	interceptors will be given a chance to process the response manually,
	or throw a new exception. If all interceptors successfully return,
	RestEasy will re-throw the original encountered exception. Note,
	however, that the response input stream may need to be reset before
	additional reads will succeed.
</para>

<programlisting>
public class ExampleInterceptor implements ClientErrorInterceptor
{
	public void handle(ClientResponse response) throws RuntimeException
	{
		try
		{
			BaseClientResponse r = (BaseClientResponse) response;
			InputStream stream = r.getStreamFactory().getInputStream();
			stream.reset();
			
			String data = response.getEntity(String.class);
		
		
			if(FORBIDDEN.equals(response.getResponseStatus()))
			{
				throw new MyCustomException("This exception will be thrown "
					+ "instead of the ClientResponseFailure");
			}
		
		}
		catch (IOException e)
		{
			//...
		}
		// If we got here, and this method returns successfully, 
		// RESTEasy will throw the original ClientResponseFailure
	}
}
</programlisting>

		<para>
		
		
        </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    
    
   <sect1 id="ClientRequest">
   <title>Manual ClientRequest API</title>
   <para>Resteasy has a manual API for invoking requests:  org.jboss.resteasy.client.ClientRequest  See the Javadoc for the full capabilities
    of this class.  Here is a simple example:</para>
<programlisting>

<![CDATA[   ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8080/some/path");
   request.header("custom-header", "value");

   // We're posting XML and a JAXB object
   request.body("application/xml", someJaxb);

   // we're expecting a String back
   ClientResponse<String> response = request.post(String.class);
   
   if (response.getStatus() == 200) // OK!
   {
      String str = response.getEntity();
   }]]>
</programlisting>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="spring_client_proxy">
        <title>Spring integration on client side</title>
        <para>
            When using spring you can generate a REST client proxy from an interface
            with the help of org.jboss.resteasy.client.spring.RestClientProxyFactoryBean.
        </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean id="echoClient" class="org.jboss.resteasy.client.spring.RestClientProxyFactoryBean"
    p:serviceInterface="a.b.c.Echo" p:baseUri="http://server.far.far.away:8080/echo" />
]]></programlisting>
   </sect1>
   
   <sect1 id="transport_layer">
     <title>Transport Layer</title>
     
     <para>
         Network communication between the client and server is handled in Resteasy,
         by default, by HttpClient (4.x) from the Apache HttpComponents project.  In general,
         the interface between the Resteasy Client Framework and the network is
         found in an implementation of
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.ClientExecutor</classname>, and
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.core.executors.ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname>,
         which uses HttpClient (4.x), is the default implementation.  Resteasy
         also ships with the following client executors, all found in the
         <code>org.jboss.resteasy.client.core.executors</code> package:
     </para>
     
     <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>ApacheHttpClientExecutor: uses HttpClient (3.x);</listitem>
         <listitem>
             URLConnectionClientExecutor: uses <classname>java.net.HttpURLConnection</classname>;
         </listitem>
         <listitem>InMemoryClientExecutor: dispatches requests to a server in the same JVM.</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
         The choice of a default executor may be overriden by calling
         <methodname>ClientRequest.setDefaultExecutorClass()</methodname>:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientRequest.setDefaultExecutorClass("org.bluemonkeydiamond.MyClientExecutor");
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         and a client executor may be passed to a specific <classname>ClientRequest</classname>:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientExecutor executor = new MyClientExecutor();
ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8081/customer", executor);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         or to a specific proxy:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientExecutor executor = new MyClientExecutor();
SimpleClient client = ProxyFactory.create(SimpleClient.class, "http://localhost:8081/customer", executor);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         Resteasy and HttpClient make reasonable default decisions so that it is possible to use the client
         framework without ever referencing HttpClient, but for some applications it may be necessary to drill
         down into the HttpClient details.  <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname> can
         be supplied with an instance of <classname>org.apache.http.client.HttpClient</classname> and
         an instance of <classname>org.apache.http.protocol.HttpContext</classname>, which can carry
         additional configuration details into the HttpClient layer.  For example, authentication
         may be configured as follows:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
// Configure HttpClient to authenticate preemptively
// by prepopulating the authentication data cache.
 
// 1. Create AuthCache instance
AuthCache authCache = new BasicAuthCache();
 
// 2. Generate BASIC scheme object and add it to the local auth cache
BasicScheme basicAuth = new BasicScheme();
authCache.put("com.bluemonkeydiamond.sippycups", basicAuth);
 
// 3. Add AuthCache to the execution context
BasicHttpContext localContext = new BasicHttpContext();
localContext.setAttribute(ClientContext.AUTH_CACHE, authCache);
 
// 4. Create client executor and proxy
httpClient = new DefaultHttpClient();
ApacheHttpClient4Executor executor = new ApacheHttpClient4Executor(httpClient, localContext);
client = ProxyFactory.create(BookStoreService.class, url, executor);
     </programlisting>

     <para>
         One default decision made by HttpClient and adopted by Resteasy is the use of
         <classname>org.apache.http.impl.conn.SingleClientConnManager</classname>,
         which manages a single socket at any given time and which
         supports the use case in which one or more invocations are made serially
         from a single thread.  For multithreaded applications, 
         <classname>SingleClientConnManager</classname> may be replaced by 
         <classname>org.apache.http.impl.conn.tsccm.ThreadSafeClientConnManager</classname>:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientConnectionManager cm = new ThreadSafeClientConnManager();
HttpClient httpClient = new DefaultHttpClient(cm);
ClientExecutor executor = new ApacheHttpClient4Executor(httpClient);
client = ProxyFactory.create(BookStoreService.class, url, executor);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         For more information about HttpClient (4.x), see the documentation
         at <ulink url="http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-client-ga/tutorial/html/">
         http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-client-ga/tutorial/html/</ulink>.
     </para>
     
     <para>
         <emphasis role="bold">Note.</emphasis> It is important to understand
         the difference between "releasing" a connection and "closing" a
         connection.  <emphasis role="bold">Releasing</emphasis> a connection
         makes it available for reuse.  <emphasis role="bold">Closing</emphasis>
         a connection frees its resources and makes it unusable.
     </para>
     <para>
         <classname>SingleClientConnManager</classname> manages
         a single socket, which it allocates to at most a single invocation
         at any given time.  Before that socket can be reused, it has to be
         released from its current use, which can occur in one of two ways.  If
         an execution of a <classname>ClientRequest</classname> or a call on
         a proxy returns a class other than <classname>ClientResponse</classname>,
         then Resteasy will take care of releasing the connection.  For example,
         in the fragments
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8081/customer/123");
String answer = request.getTarget(String.class);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         or
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
RegistryStats stats = ProxyFactory.create(RegistryStats.class, "http://localhost:8081/customer/123");
RegistryData data = stats.get();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
        Resteasy will release the connection under the covers.  The only counterexample is the case
        in which the response is an instance of <classname>InputStream</classname>, which must
        be closed explicitly.
     </para>
     
     <para>
         On the other hand, if the result of an invocation is an instance of
         <classname>ClientResponse</classname>, then one of two additional steps must be taken
         to release the connection.  If some version of the overloaded method
         <methodname>ClientResponse.getEntity()</methodname> is called, then
         Resteasy will release the connection (unless the entity is an instance
         of <classname>InputStream</classname>).  If the entity is ignored,
         then the connection must be released explicitly:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8081:/customer/123"));
ClientResponse&lt;?&gt; response = request.get();
System.out.println(response.getStatus());
response.releaseConnection();
response = request.delete("123");
System.out.println(response.getStatus());
response.releaseConnection();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         Again, releasing a connection only makes it available
         for another use. <emphasis role="bold">It does not normally close the socket.</emphasis>
     </para>
         
     <para>
         On the other hand,
         <methodname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor.finalize()</methodname> will close any open
         sockets, but only if it created the <classname>HttpClient</classname> it has been
         using.  If an <classname>HttpClient</classname> has been passed into the
         <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname>, then the user is responsible
         for closing the connections:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
HttpClient httpClient = new DefaultHttpClient();
ApacheHttpClient4Executor executor = new ApacheHttpClient4Executor(httpClient);
ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8081/customer"), executor);
...
httpClient.getConnectionManager().shutdown();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         Note that if <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname> has created its own
         instance of <classname>HttpClient</classname>, it is not necessary to wait
         for <methodname>finalize()</methodname> to close open sockets.  The
         <classname>ClientExecutor</classname> interface has a <methodname>close()</methodname>
         method for this purpose:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8081/customer/123"));
ClientResponse&lt;Customer&gt; response = request.get(Customer.class);
response.releaseConnection();
request.delete();
request.getExecutor().close();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         The call to <methodname>ClientResponse.releaseConnection()</methodname>
         makes the underlying connection available for the 
         <methodname>delete()</methodname> invocation.  The call to
         <methodname>ClientRequest.getExecutor().close()</methodname>
         closes the underlying connection.
     </para>
   </sect1>
   
   <sect1 id="transport_layer_exception_handling">
     <title>Transport Layer Exception Handling</title>
     
     <para>
         The exception mechanism described in <xref linkend="Client_error_handling"/>
         handles server responses that return with an error status.  In the case that
         an error occurs in the transport layer, a client proxy must throw a
         <classname>RuntimeException</classname> because its interface may or may
         not declare an appropriate throws clause.  In order to allow fine grained
         exception handling, Resteasy has a rich tree of exceptions, derived from
         <classname>RuntimeException</classname>, into which the structure of
         exceptions thrown by HttpClient 3 and the structure of exceptions thrown
         by HttpClient 4 can be mapped isomorphically.  That tree lives in package
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.exception</classname> and is rooted at
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.exception.ResteasyClientException</classname>:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
java.lang.RuntimeException
   |ResteasyClientException
   |  |ResteasyHttpException
   |  |  |ResteasyHttpContentTooLargeException
   |  |  |ResteasyHttpRecoverableException
   |  |  |ResteasyMethodNotSupportedException
   |  |  |ResteasyProtocolException
   |  |  |  |ResteasyAuthenticationException
   |  |  |  |  |ResteasyAuthChallengeException
   |  |  |  |  |ResteasyCredentialsNotAvailableException
   |  |  |  |  |ResteasyInvalidCredentialsException
   |  |  |  |  |ResteasyNTLMEngineException
   |  |  |  |ResteasyMalformedChallengeException
   |  |  |  |ResteasyMalformedCookieException
   |  |  |  |  |ResteasyCookieRestrictionViolationException
   |  |  |  |ResteasyNonRepeatableRequestException
   |  |  |  |  |ResteasyRedirectException
   |  |  |  |  |  |ResteasyCircularRedirectException
   |  |  |  |  |  |ResteasyInvalidRedirectLocationException
   |  |  |  |ResteasyTunnelRefusedException
   |  |  |  |ResteasyUnsupportedHttpVersionException
   |  |  |ResteasyURIException
   |  |ResteasyIOException
   |  |  |ResteasyClientProtocolException
   |  |  |ResteasyConnectionClosedException
   |  |  |ResteasyConnectTimeoutException
   |  |     |ResteasyConnectionPoolTimeoutException
   |  |  |ResteasyHttpHostConnectException
   |  |  |ResteasyMalformedChunkCodingException
   |  |  |ResteasyNoHttpResponseException
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         According to Section 1.3 "HTTP exception handling" of the HttpClient 4 documentation
         (<ulink url="http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-core-ga/tutorial/html/fundamentals.html">
         http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-core-ga/tutorial/html/fundamentals.html</ulink>)
     </para>
     
     <blockquote>
All HttpCore components potentially throw two types of exceptions: IOException in case of an I/O
failure such as socket timeout or an socket reset and HttpException that signals an HTTP failure
such as a violation of the HTTP protocol. Usually I/O errors are considered non-fatal and recoverable,
whereas HTTP protocol errors are considered fatal and cannot be automatically recovered from.
     </blockquote>
     
     <para>
         The tree of <classname>IOException</classname>s thrown by HttpClient 4 maps into the tree
         rooted at <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.exception.ResteasyIOException</classname>,
         and the tree of <classname>HttpException</classname>s maps into the tree rooted at
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.exception.ResteasyHttpException</classname>.
     </para>
     
     <para>
         In HttpClient 3, all exceptions, including 
         <classname>org.apache.commons.httpclient.HttpException</classname> are derived from
         <classname>java.io.IOException</classname>, and they are mapped into a tree rooted at
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.exception.ResteasyIOException</classname>.  See
         <ulink url="http://hc.apache.org/httpclient-3.x/exception-handling.html">
         http://hc.apache.org/httpclient-3.x/exception-handling.html</ulink> for the details.
     </para>
   </sect1>
   
   <sect1 id="transport_layer_entity_buffering">
     <title>Transport Layer Entity Buffering</title>
     
     <para>
       If an entity is very large, a file, for example,
       <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname> can be configured to store it in the file
       system, instead of attempting to keep it all in memory, if the size of the entity exceeds a
       certain threshold.  The threshold is expressed in either bytes, kilobytes, megabytes, or
       gigabytes, and the unit used by an instance of <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname>
       can be configured by calling the <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname> method
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
public void setFileUploadMemoryUnit(String pMemoryUnit);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
     where the value of <code>pMemoryUnit</code> may be one of
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
public static final String BYTE_MEMORY_UNIT = "BY";
public static final String KILOBYTE_MEMORY_UNIT = "KB";
public static final String MEGABYTE_MEMORY_UNIT = "MB";
public static final String GIGABYTE_MEMORY_UNIT = "GB";
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
       The default unit is megabytes. The threshold, expressed in terms of the configured unit,
       can be configured by calling the <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname> method
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
public void setFileUploadInMemoryThresholdLimit(int pInMemoryThresholdLimit);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
       The default value is 1, i.e., the default threshold is 1 megabyte.  The directory in which
       entities are stored can be configured by calling the
       <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname> method
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
public void setFileUploadTempFileDir(File pTempFileDir);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
       The default directory is the value of <code>System.getProperty("java.io.tmpdir")</code>.
     </para>
     
     <para>
       To use the buffering facility, then, create an instance of <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname>,
       configure it, and pass it to a <classname>ClientRequest</classname> or a proxy:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ApacheHttpClient4Executor executor = new ApacheHttpClient4Executor();
executor.setFileUploadMemoryUnit(ApacheHttpClient4Executor.GIGABYTE_MEMORY_UNIT);
executor.setFileUploadInMemoryThresholdLimit(4);
ClientRequest request = new ClientRequest("http://localhost:8081/hello/", executor);
     </programlisting>
   </sect1>
</chapter>

