<chapter id="json">
    <title>JSON Support via Jackson</title>
    <para>Besides the Jettision JAXB adapter for JSON, Resteasy also support integration with the Jackson project.
        Many users find the output from Jackson much much nicer than the Badger format or Mapped format provided by
        Jettison.
        Jackson lives at http://jackson.codehaus.org. It allows you to easily marshal Java objects to and from JSON.
        It has a Java Bean based model as well as JAXB like APIs. Resteasy integrates with the JavaBean model as
        described
        at this url: http://jackson.codehaus.org/Tutorial.
    </para>
    <para>While Jackson does come with its own JAX-RS integration. Resteasy expanded it a little. To include
        it within your project, just add this maven dependency to your build.
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
    <repository>
       <id>jboss</id>
       <url>>http://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/</url>
    </repository>

       ...
    <dependency>
       <groupId>org.jboss.resteasy</groupId>
       <artifactId>resteasy-jackson-provider</artifactId>
       <version>2.3.4.Final.HCA</version>
    </dependency>
 ]]></programlisting>
    <para>The first extra piece that Resteasy added to the integration was
        to support "application/*+json". Jackson would only accept "application/json" and "text/json" as valid
        media types. This allows you to create json-based media types and still
        let Jackson marshal things for you. For example:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
@Path("/customers")
public class MyService {

   @GET
   @Produces("application/vnd.customer+json")
   public Customer[] getCustomers() {}
}
]]>
    </programlisting>
    <para>Another problem that occurs is when you are using the Resteasy JAXB providers alongside Jackson.
        You may want to use Jettision and JAXB to output your JSON instead of Jackson. In this case, you must
        either not install the Jackson provider, or use the annotation
        @org.jboss.resteasy.annotations.providers.NoJackson
        on your JAXB annotated classes. For example:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[

    @XmlRootElement
    @NoJackson
    public class Customer {...}

    @Path("/customers")
    public class MyService {

       @GET
       @Produces("application/vnd.customer+json")
       public Customer[] getCustomers() {}
    }
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
    <para>
        If you can't annotate the JAXB class with @NoJackson, then you can
        use the annotation on a method parameter. For example:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[

        @XmlRootElement
        public class Customer {...}

        @Path("/customers")
        public class MyService {

           @GET
           @Produces("application/vnd.customer+json")
           @NoJackson
           public Customer[] getCustomers() {}

           @POST
           @Consumes("application/vnd.customer+json")
           public void createCustomer(@NoJackson Customer[] customers) {...}
        }
        ]]>
    </programlisting>
    <sect1 id="Possible_Jackson_Problems">
        <title>Possible Conflict With JAXB Provider</title>
        <para>
            If your Jackson classes are annotated with JAXB annotations and you have the resteasy-jaxb-provider in your
            classpath, you may trigger the Jettision JAXB marshalling code. To turn off the JAXB json marshaller
            use the @org.jboss.resteasy.annotations.providers.jaxb.IgnoreMediaTypes("application/*+json") on your
            classes.
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
