<chapter id="Migration_from_older_versions">
   <title>Migration from older versions</title>
   <sect1 id="migrating_1.2_1.2.1">
     <title>Migrating from 1.2.GA to 1.2.1.GA</title>
     <para>
      Methods @Deprecated within 1.2.GA have been removed.  This is in the Client Framework and has to do with all references to Apache HTTP Client.  You must now create an ClientExecutor if you want to manage your Apache HTTP Client
      sessions.
     </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="Migrating_to_Resteasy_Beta_6">
      <title>Migrating from 1.1 to 1.2</title>

      <para>

         <itemizedlist>
             <listitem>
                The resteasy-maven-import artifact has been renamed to resteasy-bom
             </listitem>
             <listitem>
                 Jettison and Fastinfoset have been broken out of the resteasy-jaxb-provider maven module.  You will now need to include resteasy-jettison-provider or resteasy-fastinfoset-provider if you use either
                 of these libraries.
             </listitem>
            <listitem>
                The constructors for ClientRequest that have a HttpClient parameter (Apache Http Client 3.1 API)  are now deprecated.  They will be removed in the final release of 1.2.  You must create a Apache hTTP Client Executor and pass it in as a parameter if you want to re-use existing Apache HttpClient sessions or do any special configuration.  The same is true for the ProxyFactoyr methods.
            </listitem>
             <!--
            <listitem>
                Apache HttpClient 4.0 is now the default client used for our ClientRequest and ProxyFactory APIs.  Version 3.1 of this library is still support.  Just allocate an executor for that instead.  Or you can set the default one used by modifying the static field ClientRequest.defaultExecutorClass.
            </listitem>
            -->
             <listitem>
                 Apache HttpClient 4.0 support is available if you want to use it.  I've had some trouble with it so it is not the default implementation yet for the client framework.
             </listitem>
             <listitem>
             It is no longer required to call RegisterBuiltin.register() to initialize the set of providers.  Too many users forgot to do this (include myself!).  You can turn this off by calling the static method ResteasyProviderFactory.setRegisterBuiltinByDefault(false)
             </listitem>
             <listitem>
                 The Embedded Container's API has changed to use org.jboss.resteasy.spi.ResteasyDeployment.  Please see embedded documentation for more details.
             </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </para>
   </sect1>
</chapter>
