<chapter id="JAX-RS_2.1_additions">
    <title>JAX-RS 2.1 Additions</title>
    <para>JAX-RS 2.1 adds more asynchronous processing support in both the
        Client and the Server API.  The specification adds a Reactive programming
        style to the Client side and Server-Sent Events (SSE) protocol support to
        both client and server.
    </para>

    <sect1>
        <title>Rective Clients API</title>
        <para>The specification defines a new type of invoker named RxInvoker, and a default
            implementation of this type named CompletionStageRxInvoker.
            CompletionStageRxInvoker implements Java 8's interface CompletionStage.
            This interface declares a large number of methods dedicated to managing
            asynchronous computations.
        </para>
        <para>There is also a new rx method which is used in a similar manner to async.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Server-Sent Events (SSE)</title>
        <para>Server-sent events provides a way to establish a one-way channel from a server
            to a client. The connection is long running and it is re-used for multiple events
            sent from the server.
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>SSE Client API</title>
            <para>
                The SSE entry point in the client API is the SseEventSource class.
                This object is constructed from a WebTarget.
                It does not duplicate any functionality in WebTarget.
                It only adds the necessary logic for SSE.
            </para>
            <para>
                Clients request an SSE connection by using the special media type
                <emphasis>text/event-stream</emphasis>
                in the Accept header.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>SSE Server API</title>
            <para>
                The SSE server API is used to accept connections and send events to one or more clients.
                A resource method that injects an SseEventSink and produces the media type
                <emphasis>text/event-stream</emphasis>
                is an SSE resource method.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Broadcasting</title>
            <para>
                SSE provides a way to broadcast events to multiple clients simultaneously.
                Multiple SseEventSink’s can be registered on a single SseBroadcaster object.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Java API for JSON Binding</title>
        <para>
            RESTEasy supports both JSON-B and JSON-P.  In accordance with the specification,
            entity providers for JSON-B take precedence over those for JSON-P for all types
            except JsonValue and its sub-types.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Asynchronous HTTP Request Processing</title>
        <para>
            RESTEasy provides a new <emphasis>ClientHttpEngine</emphasis> implementation that
            provides asynchronous HTTP request support.  The new engine uses
            <emphasis>HttpAsyncClient</emphasis> from the Apache <emphasis>HttpComponents</emphasis>
            project.  RESTEasy's default async engine implementation class is
            <emphasis>ApacheHttpAsyncClient4Engine</emphasis>.  It can be set as the active
            engine by calling method <emphasis>useAsyncHttpEngine</emphasis> in
            <emphasis>ResteasyClientBuilder</emphasis>.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
    Client asyncClient = new ResteasyClientBuilder().useAsyncHttpEngine()
                             .build();
    Future&lt;Response&gt; future = asyncClient
                             .target("http://locahost:8080/test").request()
                             .async().get();
    Response res = future.get();
    Assert.assertEquals(HttpResponseCodes.SC_OK, res.getStatus());
    String entity = res.readEntity(String.class);
        </programlisting>
        <sect2>
            <title>InvocationCallbacks</title>
            <para>
                InvocationCallbacks are called from within the io-threads and thus must not block or else
                the application may slow down to a halt. Reading the response is safe because the response
                is buffered in memory, as are other async and in-memory client-invocations that submit-calls
                returning a future not containing Response, InputStream or Reader.
            </para>
            <programlisting>
   final CountDownLatch latch = new CountDownLatch(1);
   Future&lt;String&gt; future = nioClient.target(generateURL("/test")).request()
         .async().get(new InvocationCallback&lt;String&gt;()
                {
                   @Override
                   public void completed(String s)
                   {
                      Assert.assertEquals("get", s);
                      latch.countDown();
                      throw new RuntimeException("for the test of it");
                   }

                   @Override
                   public void failed(Throwable error)
                   {
                   }
                });
   String entity = future.get();
   Assert.assertEquals("get", entity);
            </programlisting>
            <para>
                InvocationCallbacks may be called seemingly "after" the future-object returns. Thus, responses
                should be handled solely in the InvocationCallback.
            </para>
            <para>
                InvocationCallbacks will see the same result as the future-object and vice versa. Thus, if the
                invocationcallback throws an exception, the future-object will not see it. This is the
                reason to handle responses only in the InvocationCallback.
            </para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Async Engine Usage Considerations</title>
            <para>
                Asynchronous IO means non-blocking IO utilizing few threads, typically at most as many
                threads as number of cores.  As such, performance may profit from fewer thread switches
                and less memory usage due to fewer thread-stacks. But doing synchronous, blocking IO (the
                invoke-methods not returning a future) may suffer, because the data has to be transferred
                piecewiese to/from the io-threads.
            </para>
            <para>
                Request-Entities are fully buffered in memory, thus <emphasis>HttpAsyncClient</emphasis>
                is unsuitable for very large uploads.  Response-Entities are buffered in memory, except
                if requesting a Response, InputStream or Reader as Result. Thus for large downloads or
                COMET one of these three return types must be requested, but there may be a performance
                penalty because the response-body is transferred piecewise from the io-threads. When
                using InvocationCallbacks, the response is always fully buffered in memory.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>