<chapter id="JAX-RS_2.1_additions">
    <title>JAX-RS 2.1 Additions</title>
    <para>JAX-RS 2.1 adds more asynchronous processing support in both the
        Client and the Server API.  The specification adds a Reactive programming
        style to the Client side and Server-Sent Events (SSE) protocol support to
        both client and server.
    </para>

    <sect1>
        <title>Rective Clients API</title>
        <para>The specification defines a new type of invoker named RxInvoker, and a default
            implementation of this type named CompletionStageRxInvoker.
            CompletionStageRxInvoker implements Java 8's interface CompletionStage.
            This interface declares a large number of methods dedicated to managing
            asynchronous computations.
        </para>
        <para>There is also a new rx method which is used in a similar manner to async.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Server-Sent Events (SSE)</title>
        <para>Server-sent events provides a way to establish a one-way channel from a server
            to a client. The connection is long running and it is re-used for multiple events
            sent from the server.
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>SSE Client API</title>
            <para>
                The SSE entry point in the client API is the SseEventSource class.
                This object is constructed from a WebTarget.
                It does not duplicate any functionality in WebTarget.
                It only adds the necessary logic for SSE.
            </para>
            <para>
                Clients request an SSE connection by using the special media type
                <emphasis>text/event-stream</emphasis>
                in the Accept header.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>SSE Server API</title>
            <para>
                The SSE server API is used to accept connections and send events to one or more clients.
                A resource method that injects an SseEventSink and produces the media type
                <emphasis>text/event-stream</emphasis>
                is an SSE resource method.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Broadcasting</title>
            <para>
                SSE provides a way to broadcast events to multiple clients simultaneously.
                Multiple SseEventSink’s can be registered on a single SseBroadcaster object.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Java API for JSON Binding</title>
        <para>
            RESTEasy supports both JSON-B and JSON-P.  In accordance with the specification,
            entity providers for JSON-B take precedence over those for JSON-P for all types
            except JsonValue and its sub-types.
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>