<chapter id="Reactive">
    <title>Reactive programming support</title>
    <para>
        JAX-RS 2.1 adds support for returning the <link linkend="CompletionStage">asynchronous 
        reactive type <code>CompletableFuture</code></link>, but
        RESTEasy supports much more than this, when it comes to asynchronous programming. 
    </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Plugable reactive types</title>
        <para>
            Out of the box, RESTEasy supports <code>CompletableFuture</code> for single events, and 
            <code>org.reactivestreams.Publisher</code> (from <link linkend="http://www.reactive-streams.org">Reactive Streams</link>)
            for multiple events.
        </para>
        <para>
            The optional modules <code>resteasy-rxjava</code> and 
            <code>resteasy-rxjava2</code> add support for the <link linkend="https://github.com/ReactiveX/RxJava">RxJava 1 and 2</link>
            reactive types, such as <code>Single</code> and <code>Observable</code>, which means if you import
            this dependency you can just start returning reactive types from those frameworks from your resource methods.
        </para>
        <para>
            Adding support for other reactive types can be done by declaring a <code>@Provider</code> for the interfaces
            <code>AsyncStreamProvider</code> (for streams) and <code>AsyncResponseProvider</code> (for single values), which
            both have a single method to convert the new reactive type into (respectively) a <code>Publisher</code> (for streams)
            or a <code>CompletionStage</code> (for single values).
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Behavior of reactive types</title>
        <para>
            Single-value reactive types behave like the specification of JAX-RS 2.1 wrt. <code>CompletionStage</code>,
            which is that the reactive value will be subscribed to, the request will be turned asynchronous, and only
            resumed when the reactive value is resolved to either a value (normal completion), or an exception.
        </para>
        <para>
            Multiple-value reactive types (streams) behave in three possible ways, depending on how the resource method
            is annotated:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Default case (no special annotation)</term>
                <listitem>
                    Collect every value until the stream is complete, then wrap into a <code>java.util.List</code> entity 
                    and send to the client.
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><code>@Produces(MediaType.SERVER_SENT_EVENTS)</code></term>
                <listitem>
                    Send each value as a Server-Sent Event. This is an alternative to the more verbose <link linkend="SSE-Server">SSE
                    server support in JAX-RS 2.1</link>.
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><code>@Stream</code></term>
                <listitem>
                    Write each value to the response as they become available. This is most useful for values you can cut in pieces,
                    such as strings, bytes, buffers, etc.
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
