<chapter id="RESTEasy_Client_Framework">
    <title>Resteasy Client API</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>JAX-RS 2.0 Client API</title>
        <para>JAX-RS 2.0 introduces a new client API so that you can make http requests to your remote RESTful web services.
        It is a 'fluent' request building API with really 3 main classes:  Client, WebTarget, and Response.  The Client
        interface is a builder of WebTarget instances.  WebTarget represents a distinct URL or URL template from which
        you can build more sub-resource WebTargets or invoke requests on.</para>
        <para>
            There are really two ways to create a Client.  Standard way, or you can use the ResteasyClientBuilder class.
            The advantage of the latter is that it gives you a few more helper methods to configure your client.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
            Client client = ClientBuilder.newClient();
            ... or...
            Client client = ClientBuilder.newBuilder().build();
            WebTarget target = client.target("http://foo.com/resource");
            Response response = target.request().get();
            String value = response.readEntity(String.class);
            response.close();  // You should close connections!

            ResteasyClient client = new ResteasyClientBuilder().build();
            ResteasyWebTarget target = client.target("http://foo.com/resource");
        </programlisting>
        <para>
            Resteasy will automatically load a set of default providers. (Basically all classes listed in all
            META-INF/services/javax.ws.rs.ext.Providers files).  Additionally, you can manually register other providers,
            filters, and interceptors through the Configuration object provided by the method call Client.configuration().
            Configuration also lets you set various configuration properties that may be needed.
        </para>
        <para>
            Each WebTarget has its own Configuration instance which inherits the components and properties registered with
            its parent.  This allows you to set specific configuration options per target resource.  For example, username
            and password.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <para>

    </para>

    <sect1>
        <title>Resteasy Proxy Framework</title>
    <para>

        The Resteasy Proxy  Framework is the mirror opposite of the JAX-RS server-side specification. Instead of using
        JAX-RS annotations to map an incoming request to your RESTFul Web Service method, the client framework builds an
        HTTP request that it uses to invoke on a remote RESTful Web Service. This remote service does not have to be a
        JAX-RS service and can be any web resource that accepts HTTP requests.
    </para>
    <para>

        Resteasy has a client proxy framework that allows you to use JAX-RS annotations to invoke on a remote HTTP
        resource.
        The way it works is that you write a Java interface and use JAX-RS annotations on methods and the interface. For
        example:
    </para>
    <para>

<programlisting>
public interface SimpleClient
{
   @GET
   @Path("basic")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   String getBasic();

   @PUT
   @Path("basic")
   @Consumes("text/plain")
   void putBasic(String body);

   @GET
   @Path("queryParam")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   String getQueryParam(@QueryParam("param")String param);

   @GET
   @Path("matrixParam")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   String getMatrixParam(@MatrixParam("param")String param);

   @GET
   @Path("uriParam/{param}")
   @Produces("text/plain")
   int getUriParam(@PathParam("param")int param);
}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>

        Resteasy has a simple API based on Apache HttpClient. You generate a proxy then you can invoke methods on the
        proxy. The invoked method gets translated to an HTTP request based on how you annotated the method and posted to
        the server. Here's how you would set this up:
    </para>
    <para>

        <programlisting>
            Client client = ClientFactory.newClient();
            WebTarget target = client.target("http://example.com/base/uri");
            ResteasyWebTarget rtarget = (ResteasyWebTarget)target;

            SimpleClient simple = rtarget.proxy(SimpleClient.class);
            client.putBasic("hello world");
        </programlisting>
        Alternatively you can use the Resteasy client extension interfaces directly:
        <programlisting>
            ResteasyClient client = new ResteasyClientBuilder().build();
            ResteasyWebTarget target = client.target("http://example.com/base/uri");

            SimpleClient simple = target.proxy(SimpleClient.class);
            client.putBasic("hello world");
        </programlisting>

    </para>
    <para>

        @CookieParam works the mirror opposite of its server-side counterpart and creates a cookie header to send to the
        server. You do not need to use @CookieParam if you allocate your own javax.ws.rs.core.Cookie object and pass it
        as
        a parameter to a client proxy method. The client framework understands that you are passing a cookie to the
        server
        so no extra metadata is needed.
    </para>
    <para>
     The framework also supports the JAX-RS locator pattern, but on the client side.  So, if you have a method annotated only with @Path, that proxy method
     will return a new proxy of the interface returned by that method.
    </para>
    <sect1 id="Custom_client-side_responses">
        <title>Abstract Responses</title>

        <para>

            Sometimes you are interested not only in the response body of a client request, but also either the response
            code and/or response headers. The Client-Proxy framework has two ways to get at this information
        </para>
        <para>


        </para>
        <para>

            You may return a javax.ws.rs.core.Response.Status enumeration from your method calls:
        </para>
        <para>

            <programlisting>
@Path("/")
public interface MyProxy {
   @POST
   Response.Status updateSite(MyPojo pojo);
}
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>

            Internally, after invoking on the server, the client proxy internals will convert the HTTP response code into
            a
            Response.Status enum.
        </para>
        <para>


        </para>
        <para>

            If you are interested in everything, you can get it with the javax.ws.rs.core.Response class:
        </para>
        <para>

            <programlisting>
@Path("/")
public interface LibraryService {

   @GET
   @Produces("application/xml")
   Response getAllBooks();
}</programlisting>
        </para>
     </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sharing_interfaces">
        <title>Sharing an interface between client and server</title>
        <para>
            It is generally possible to share an interface between the client and server. In this scenario, you just
            have your JAX-RS services implement an annotated interface
            and then reuse that same interface to create client proxies to invoke on the client-side.
        </para>

    </sect1>
    </sect1>
    
    
    

   
   <sect1 id="transport_layer">
     <title>Apache HTTP Client 4.x and other backends</title>
     
     <para>
         Network communication between the client and server is handled in Resteasy,
         by default, by HttpClient (4.x) from the Apache HttpComponents project.  In general,
         the interface between the Resteasy Client Framework and the network is
         found in an implementation of
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.jaxrs.ClientHttpEngine</classname>, and
         <classname>org.jboss.resteasy.client.jaxrs.engines.ApacheHttpClient4Engine</classname>,
         which uses HttpClient (4.x), is the default implementation.  Resteasy
         also ships with the following client engines, all found in the
         <code>org.jboss.resteasy.client.jaxrs.engines</code> package:
     </para>
     
     <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
             URLConnectionClientExecutor: uses <classname>java.net.HttpURLConnection</classname>;
         </listitem>
         <listitem>InMemoryClientExecutor: dispatches requests to a server in the same JVM.</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
         and a client executor may be passed to a specific <classname>ClientRequest</classname>:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ResteasyClient client = new ResteasyClientBuilder().httpEngine(engine).build();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         Resteasy and HttpClient make reasonable default decisions so that it is possible to use the client
         framework without ever referencing HttpClient, but for some applications it may be necessary to drill
         down into the HttpClient details.  <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Engine</classname> can
         be supplied with an instance of <classname>org.apache.http.client.HttpClient</classname> and
         an instance of <classname>org.apache.http.protocol.HttpContext</classname>, which can carry
         additional configuration details into the HttpClient layer.  For example, authentication
         may be configured as follows:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
// Configure HttpClient to authenticate preemptively
// by prepopulating the authentication data cache.
 
// 1. Create AuthCache instance
AuthCache authCache = new BasicAuthCache();
 
// 2. Generate BASIC scheme object and add it to the local auth cache
AuthScheme basicAuth = new BasicScheme();
authCache.put(new HttpHost("sippycups.bluemonkeydiamond.com"), basicAuth);
 
// 3. Add AuthCache to the execution context
BasicHttpContext localContext = new BasicHttpContext();
localContext.setAttribute(ClientContext.AUTH_CACHE, authCache);
 
// 4. Create client executor and proxy
DefaultHttpClient httpClient = new DefaultHttpClient();
ApacheHttpClient4Engine engine = new ApacheHttpClient4Engine(httpClient, localContext);
ResteasyClient client = new ResteasyClientBuilder().httpEngine(engine).build();
     </programlisting>

     <para>
         One default decision made by HttpClient and adopted by Resteasy is the use of
         <classname>org.apache.http.impl.conn.SingleClientConnManager</classname>,
         which manages a single socket at any given time and which
         supports the use case in which one or more invocations are made serially
         from a single thread.  For multithreaded applications, 
         <classname>SingleClientConnManager</classname> may be replaced by 
         <classname>org.apache.http.impl.conn.tsccm.ThreadSafeClientConnManager</classname>:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ClientConnectionManager cm = new ThreadSafeClientConnManager();
HttpClient httpClient = new DefaultHttpClient(cm);
ApacheHttpClient4Engine engine = new ApacheHttpClient4Engine(httpClient);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         For more information about HttpClient (4.x), see the documentation
         at <ulink url="http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-client-ga/tutorial/html/">
         http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-client-ga/tutorial/html/</ulink>.
     </para>
     
     <para>
         <emphasis role="bold">Note.</emphasis> It is important to understand
         the difference between "releasing" a connection and "closing" a
         connection.  <emphasis role="bold">Releasing</emphasis> a connection
         makes it available for reuse.  <emphasis role="bold">Closing</emphasis>
         a connection frees its resources and makes it unusable.
     </para>
     <para>
         <classname>SingleClientConnManager</classname> manages
         a single socket, which it allocates to at most a single invocation
         at any given time.  Before that socket can be reused, it has to be
         released from its current use, which can occur in one of two ways.  If
         an execution of a request or a call on
         a proxy returns a class other than <classname>Response</classname>,
         then Resteasy will take care of releasing the connection.  For example,
         in the fragments
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
WebTarget target = client.target("http://localhost:8081/customer/123");
String answer = target.request().get(String.class);
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         or
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
ResteasyWebTarget target = client.target("http://localhost:8081/customer/123");
RegistryStats stats = target.proxy(RegistryStats.class);
RegistryData data = stats.get();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
        Resteasy will release the connection under the covers.  The only counterexample is the case
        in which the response is an instance of <classname>InputStream</classname>, which must
        be closed explicitly.
     </para>
     
     <para>
         On the other hand, if the result of an invocation is an instance of
         <classname>Response</classname>, then Response.close() method must be used to released the connection.
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
WebTarget target = client.target("http://localhost:8081/customer/123");
Response response = target.request().get();
System.out.println(response.getStatus());
response.close();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         You should probably execute this in a try/finally block.  Again, releasing a connection only makes it available
         for another use. <emphasis role="bold">It does not normally close the socket.</emphasis>
     </para>
         
     <para>
         On the other hand,
         <methodname>ApacheHttpClient4Engine.finalize()</methodname> will close any open
         sockets, but only if it created the <classname>HttpClient</classname> it has been
         using.  If an <classname>HttpClient</classname> has been passed into the
         <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Executor</classname>, then the user is responsible
         for closing the connections:
     </para>
     
     <programlisting>
HttpClient httpClient = new DefaultHttpClient();
ApacheHttpClient4Engine executor = new ApacheHttpClient4Engine(httpClient);
...
httpClient.getConnectionManager().shutdown();
     </programlisting>
     
     <para>
         Note that if <classname>ApacheHttpClient4Engine</classname> has created its own
         instance of <classname>HttpClient</classname>, it is not necessary to wait
         for <methodname>finalize()</methodname> to close open sockets.  The
         <classname>ClientHttpEngine</classname> interface has a <methodname>close()</methodname>
         method for this purpose.
     </para>

    <para>
        Finally, if your javax.ws.rs.client.Client class has created the engine automatically for you, you should
        call Client.close() and this will clean up any socket connections.
    </para>
     
   </sect1>
   

</chapter>

